<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe resolution of a right religion Touching the controuersies, that are nowe in England. Written by C.S.</title>
            <author>C. S., fl. 1590.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21482</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100915</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836742</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836742</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1028</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1028)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1186:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe resolution of a right religion Touching the controuersies, that are nowe in England. Written by C.S.</title>
                  <author>C. S., fl. 1590.</author>
                  <author>Shutte, Christopher, d. 1626, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Roger Ward, for Iohn Proctor, and are to be sold at his shop upon Holborne Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>C.S. = Christopher Shutte?.</note>
                  <note>Pages 12-13 misnumbered 11 and 15.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1028:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1028:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Briefe reſolution of a right Religion.</p>
            <p>TOVCHING THE CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies, that are nowe in England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> C. S.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PRO. 15.32.</bibl>
               <p>He that refuſeth to be reformed deſpiſeth his owne ſoule: but he that ſubmitteth himſelfe to correction is wiſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON. <hi>Printed by Roger Ward, for Iohn Proctor, and are to be ſold at his ſhop vpon Holborne Bridge.</hi> 1590.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1028:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1028:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou haſt (courteous Reader) heere offered vnto thy viewe, a ſmall booke conteining the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of a true Religion. It is garniſhed with no great eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or rhetoricall floriſhe, as manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting my intent therin to be more to delight the inward heart, with matter of ſubſtance, then the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waed care, with words of trifling daliance. The poſitions I hope will proue true, the queſtion not doubtfull, though dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to my ſelfe, in that I ſhall hazard my perſon in run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vppon the cragged Rockes of the peſtilent toonged Papiſtes: I truſt, notwithſtanding the ſhippe of my ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie will be ſtrong inough, if not to breake the rockes, yet to beare the bruntes of all ſuch ſtormie and tempeſtuous acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes as winde and weather ſhall throwe vpon me ſayling in ſo troubleſome ſeas. howbeit I meane well euen to the Romiſh Catholikes themſelues, whom earneſtly I would requeſt to reade this ſmall worke with a ſingle eye, and with an indifferent minde, not caried away with inraged rancor, or woonted obſtinacie: for I will not feare to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues Iudges of the cauſe, if they haue their eyes to ſee, or wils to iudge with indifferencie. I haue not runne ouer all matters of both ſides, for neither could I in ſo ſmal a roume, onely and eſpecially I haue leuelled at the verie foundation: Read it through therefore (gentle Reader) with no leſſe good minde then I wrote it, and then I doubt not but thou wilt in fine be reſolued with me of a right Religion: If my worke want learning, in recompence thereof I pray thee accept my good will, wherin is no defect. Thus not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of thy humanitie, hoping well alſo of thy diuinitie, I commend this my booke to thy gratefull curteſie, and bid thee moſt heartely farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale in Chriſto.</salute> 
               <signed>C. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:1028:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>R. Armin in praiſe and commendation of this briefe <hi>Reſolution of a right Religion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are manie that haue tooke vpon them to ſet downe the poyntes of true Religion, and haue aptly argued of particular partes, yea and rightly diſciphered the ample Rules of trueth, amongeſt whome as chiefe, this learned ſtudent, C.S. hath ſufficiently plainely and profoundly plac'd it before our eyes, and hauing quite ſuppreſt falſe doctrine hath preſented to our viewe, this right reſolution and I in this behalfe will ſay, that the papiſt may well knocke himſelfe on the breſt, ſaying a Confiteor, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vaine ſignes of repentance of his ſinnes, but if he looke nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly vnto it, he ſhall finde it nothing but mockerie and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</p>
            <p>The other vitious and deteſtable ſect, are Martineſſes, who ſee ſo farre into matters, that they ouerſee themſelues, wreſting thinges from the right ſence to the wrong, making ſhew of zeale when it is meere follie, therefore let them know here is the right religion, though a briefe reſolution, ſhort and ſweete, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you that will be heyres of heauen, and you zealous prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes wiſh him wel whoſe imployed ſtudie was, and is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct you to the trueth, and therfore hold euery ſect falſe, whoſe rules he doth contradict, and withall patience waite for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and labour ſo that you may be found of him without ſpot and blameleſſe.</p>
            <p>Surely that day ought to be fearefull to the wicked, but of vs that ſhould be moſt deſired, knowing aſſuredlie that there is no condemnation to thoſe which are in Chriſt Ieſus, and his great kindnes and meekenes when hee commeth to make vs liue with him for euer in heauen. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1028:3"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE RESOLVTION OF a right Religion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat controuerſie hath long bin betweene the Papiſts and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes (as they are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tearmed) whether of them be the true church, for it is agreed of both ſides, that <hi>Extra Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam non eſt ſalus.</hi> but ſurely me thinks it is a queſtion, ſcarſe queſtionable: for, the papiſtical Romiſhe Church arrogateth, that they are the true church: and our Religion, grounded out of the worde of God, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth vs to be of the true church, for we are builded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſacred writinges of the Prophetes and Apoſtles Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe being the<note n="a" place="margin">Epheſ. 2.20.</note> corner ſtone: their church, or rather ſynagogue of Sathan is builded vpon vnwritten verities and depraued ſacred trueth, the pope of Rome, a man, nay<note n="b" place="margin">Reue. 13.1</note> a beaſt, with ſeuen heades and tenne hornes, and vpon his hornes tenne crownes, and vppon his heades the names of blaſphemie, being the head thereof. We imbrace Paule, we imbrace Peter, and yet we renounce the Pope, who vainly boaſteth himſelfe to be Peters ſucceſſour, in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the Pope is neither like to Peter, in doctrine, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1028:4"/> nor religion, and in vaine ſhall the pope boaſt to haue his place, when he commeth nothing neere vnto, in the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of his perſon, nor in the doctrine of the Apoſtles, for in this reſpect there is as much difference betweene them, as betwixt blacke and white, light and darkeneſſe, heauen and hell, as afterward ſhalbe manifeſted, Chriſt hath forewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs that there ſhall ariſe<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 24.24.</note> falſe Chriſtes, and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and ſhall ſhew great ſignes, and wonders to deceiue (if it were poſſible) the verie elect. Paule hath giuen vs a good caueat, let no man (ſaith he) deceiue himſelfe: &amp; againe, let euery man take heede howe he buildeth: And he addeth this rule, to know<note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.18.</note> aſſuredly the true and right foundation: for (ſaith he) other foundation can no man lay, but that which is layd alreadie, which (ſaith hee) is Ieſus Chriſt. The ſame Paule in his Epiſtle to the Galathians, ſaith,<note n="e" place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> if we, or an Angell from heauen, preach vnto you anie other Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell then that we haue preached, <hi>Anathema eſto,</hi> let him be accurſed: And this ſentence he iterateth, a ſecond time. If we are bidden not to beleue Angels from heauen, if they teache doctrine contrary to Paules, will aine man then be ſo fooliſh as to beleeue the pope vpon his word and vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten verities, teaching matters contrarie, not onely to Paule, but to Peter and to all the whole body of the ſacred ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? When<note n="f" place="margin">Luke 16.</note> Diues was in hell, and caſt vp his eyes and ſaw Lazarus in Abrahams boſome, and being in torments could not obtaine of Abraham, that Lazarus might dip hys finger in water and coole his toonge, becauſe hee was tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in that flame, He did then beſeeche Abraham, that he would ſend Lazarus to his fathers houſe (for he had fiue brethren) that he might teſtifie to them, leaſt they alſo came in that place of torment: But whether did he referre them? They haue (ſaith Abraham) Moſes, and the Prophets, let them heare them? for if they will not heare them, neither will they beleeue, though one riſe from the dead.</p>
            <p>Thus we are referred to build our beliefe vpon Moſes,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1028:4"/> and the prophets. Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, and commandeth vs<note n="g" place="margin">Iohn. 5 39</note> to ſearch the ſcriptures: for (ſaith he) they are they that teſtifie of me. So that the people are bolde to heare Chriſt, Moſes, and the prophets and apoſtles, with this clauſe alſo added, that if any, though an Angell from heauen, teach do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine contrarie vnto them, <hi>Anathema ſit,</hi> wee muſt holde him accurſed: ſo that we are not to beleeue the Pope, nor his vnwritten verities, nor generall Counſels, nor yet anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers, no not Angels themſelues, though comming from heauen, if they teach matter contrarie to the ſacred ſcriptures: &amp; as the people are to hear ſuch kind of Teachers ſo are alſo all that take vpon them the office of teaching, or of Apoſtleſhip, not to teach doctrines of men, or their owne fantaſies, or blind dreames, but onely ſuch ſtuffe as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue from God. Moſes, he gaue the lawe to the Iſraelits, but he did it by commandement from the Lord, and ſpake as from his mouth. What maner power the prophetes gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally had, is very well deſcribed in Ezechiell. Thou<note n="h" place="margin">Ezek. 3.18</note> ſonne of man (ſaith the Lord) I haue geuen thee to be a Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to the houſe of Iſraell, therefore thou ſhalt heare the worde out of my mouth, and thou ſhalt declare it to them from me.</p>
            <p>Look to the Apoſtles, and ſee what commiſſion they had: Goe (ſaith Chriſt)<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 27.19</note> and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the father, the ſonne, and the holy Ghoſt, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them to keepe all thinges whatſoeuer I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded you: ſo the apoſtles commiſſion was to teach that, which they had receiued from Chriſt. Chriſt himſelfe the ſonne of the euerliuing God, in reſpect that hee was an apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle or meſſenger ſent from God his Father, anſwereth the Iewes in the ſeuenth of Iohn, ſaying: My<note n="i" place="margin">Iohn. 16.</note> doctrine is not mine, but his that ſent me: So Chriſt himſelfe taught no other doctrine, but that which he had from his father. And S. Paule, as a faithfull Apoſtle affyrmeth to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hians, that he<note n="k" place="margin">1 Cor. 11</note> receiued that of the Lord, which he deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1028:5"/> vnto them. Thus wee ſee that the apoſtles ſpake from the mouth of Chriſt, Chriſt from the mouth of his Father, and all both Chriſt and the Apoſtles, Moſes and the prophetes, ſpake as from the mouth of God, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo verified by that one ſaying of the Authour to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues: God<note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 1, 1</note> in times paſt diuers waies ſpake vnto the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by the Prophetes, but in theſe laſt daies he hath ſpoken to vs by his ſonne. And Paule telleth Timothy, that all ſcripture<note n="m" place="margin">2 Tim. 3, 16</note> is giuen by diuine inſpiration, and written as with the finger of God, who is all trueth, and therefor it is impoſſible, ſhould either lie or erre.</p>
            <p>Therefore touching matters of religion, let God alone be heard, and the ſacred Scriptures produced for the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of that religion which ſhall be acceptable in his eies. For a mans faith is to bee builded vppon the ſureſt anchor and<note n="m" place="margin">2 Tim. 3, 16</note> rocke, and in ſuch ſort that neither windes nor waues be able to remooue it: and that muſt be as Chriſt teacheth, vpon his woord, which is infallible and neuer fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth. And all, both reaſon and diuinitie ſo perſwadeth: for that ſaying of Paule is true: Let<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 7.14</note> God be true, and euerie man a lier. It is well knowne, and dayly experience can tel vs, that men may erre and goe awrie, but he<note n="o" place="margin">1 Ioh, 5.10</note> that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not God, maketh him a lier, as S. Iohn ſaith, which cannot be without horrible blaſphemie.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore not build our faith and religion vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, be he Auguſtine, Cyprian, Ambroſe, Hierome or whoſoeuer, nor vpon generall Councels, for they were alſo compounded of men, and <hi>Humanum eſt errare,</hi> Men may erre: therefore no queſtion but they might erre. And if in any any thing they doo not erre, it is becauſe they haue the word of trueth, and of ſacred Scripture for their confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or els they muſt needs erre. So that all thoſe ancient Fathers and generall Counſels, they muſt all drawe water from the pure fountaine, the ſacred word of trueth, or els they doo nothing els but preach the puddle of their owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1028:5"/> which if they ſhould doo, though they were An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels from heauen, we muſt not beleeue them, nay, <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſit,</hi> we muſt hold him accurſed, by the rule of Paule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
            <p>The woorde of God deliuered as from the mouth and hand of God, being laide as a foundation, wee are not to doubt but that our religion builded thereupon is moſt ſure and certaine, neuer able vtterly to bee ouerthrowne with all the power and pollicie of Antichriſt and his adherents, bee they neuer ſo ſubtil in the one, or ful of fortitude in the other: For why? Chriſt the head of his Church is the defender thereof, and the confounder of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>The Papiſtes and enemies of the true Church of God, they call vs Heretikes by a metaphoricall ſpeach borrowed from themſelues, and giue railing ſentence vpon bs, when they are no longer able to conuince our reaſons, ſhewing therein their malignant tongues and malicious hearts: but we anſwere with Paule, that with that which they call he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, we ſerue the liuing God. They call our religion a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned doctrine, attainted long ago by general, Councels: If they ſhew me the reuealed counſell from God, I wil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue them: and of generall Counſels, ſome are meere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant and contrarie one to another, ſo that they are of litle credite But what if it be condemned by men, if it be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of God, what neede we care? We knowe that at Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem they held a councel together to put<note n="p" place="margin">Math. 26.4</note> Chriſt to death as a malefactor, yea, and condemned him. Was therfore his doctrine euer the worſe, or was it therefore ſo, becauſe they condemned him? Did they not hold a councell againſt Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen, and ſtone him to death? and yet Stephen is recorded to be a man full of<note n="q" place="margin">Act. 6.12</note> faith, and of power.</p>
            <p>What will the deceitfull Papiſtes ſay of Peter, their Popes predeceſſour? (as they vainely boaſt) There was a generall councell held againſt him alſo, and condemning his doctrine, ſcourged him and the reſt of the Apoſtles, with an
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1028:6"/> inhibition that they ſhould not teach any more in the name of Ieſus.</p>
            <p>If their general councels be of force to condemne vs and our religion, I ſee no reaſon, but that their religion ſhould be alſo condemned by the former councell againſt Peter: but Peters doctrine was true, notwithſtanding the Counſell: and ſo may ours, notwithſtanding their Councels againſt vs: For we (as I haue oft ſaid) builde our religion vppon Chriſt, vpon Peter, the apoſtles, and prophets.</p>
            <p>The Papiſtes therefore do both fooliſhlie and ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paint out the beautie of their Church, by the tytle of vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſalitie, and thereupon (as I ſuppoſe) they glorie to call themſelues Catholikes.</p>
            <p>The Pope (ſay they) holdeth the Apoſtolicall Sea, and the Byſhops that be annointed and conſecrated by him (ſo that they be trimmed with fillets and Myters) doo repreſent the Church, and ought to be taken for the Church, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they cannot er, becauſe they are conſecrated to the Lord: which conſequent alſo followeth not. For Aaron and other rulers of Iſraell alſo were conſecrate to the Lord: but Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron and his ſonnes after they were made Prieſtes, did yet erre when they<note place="margin">Exo. 31.4</note> made the calfe.</p>
            <p>But let vs examine the premiſes. Wilt thou (ſimple pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt) haue vniuerſalitie a contiuall badge of the church? wilt thou haue the true Church to conſiſt in ſuch outward glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhew? Then was the chiefe Prieſts, the Scribes and Phariſes, who were aſſembled to kil Chriſt the true church: and then ſhal Chriſt and his apoſtles, (few in number, and diſpearſed abroad) be the falſe church. For the glorie of the outward Church remained in the chiefe prieſtes, Scribes, and Phariſes, &amp; yet who be ſo blaſphemous as to dare ſay, that they were the true Church, who crucified the Lord of life? So that (ſilly papiſts) neuer deceiue the world with this gloſe: for your outward pomp of your church is rather (you ſee) an argument of a falſe church, than of a true Church.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:1028:6"/>
            <p>By this reaſon of the papiſtes, the foure<note n="t" place="margin">1. King 22.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> hundreth Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets which lied to Achab, ſhould haue repreſented the true Churche: but the Churche was indeed on Micheas ſide, being indeede but one man alone, and vnregarded, but out of whoſe mouth came trueth. Did not the falſe prophets in reſemblance beare both the face and name of the Church, when they did with one violent aſſault riſe vp againſt Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and with threatning boaſted, that it was not poſſible that the<note n="v" place="margin">Iere. 18.18.</note> law, ſhould periſh from the prieſt, counſell from the wiſe, and the word from the Prophet? Ieremie alone was ſent againſt the whole companie of the Prophets, to declare from the Lord, that it ſhoulde come to paſſe that the lawe ſhould periſh from the prieſt, counſell from the wiſe man, and the worde from the Proophet: and yet all men knowe that Ieremie was in the right and of the true Church, and all the reſt againſt him, in a maruellous errour.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, that trueth is not tyed to the multitude of men, or to the title of vniuerſalitie, nor to the outward gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring pompe, but rather <hi>contrà.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the olde world, did not Noah and his family (being verie few in number in reſpect of all the worlde beſide) did not they (I ſay) repreſent the Church of God at that time? Doth not Chriſt often call his, a little flocke? Doth not Chriſt ſay that<note n="x" place="margin">Math. 7.13.</note> wide is the gate and broad is the way that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there be that enter that way? Doth hee not alſo adde that ſtraight is the gate, and narrowe is the way that leadeth vnto life, and fewe there be that finde it? What doth all this proue, but that the feweſt vſually are the Church of God, and vniuerſalities and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, they are ſo farre from beeing markes of the true Church, that they rather euidently bewray the ſynagogue of Sathan?</p>
            <p>The Papiſts are ſtill buſie with vs, and they thinke they driue vs to a hard ſtraight, when they demand of vs where our church was manie hundred yeres agoe; for they ſay that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1028:7"/> the Church muſt conſiſt of an alwaies appearing forme, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to the eye and that it may be alwaies poynted out with the finger in apparent ſhewe. Truely this anſwere is eaſie to diſſolue this which they make ſo knotted an argument: for though papiſtes like carnall and ſenſuall men can iudge of noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng but that which they ſee with outward eyes, yet Proteſtantes (as they tearme them) God hath endued them with better vnderſtanding. Let them aunſwere me what forme of the Church ſhined in outward ſhewe, when He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias complained and bewayled that he<note n="z" place="margin">1. King. 19.11.</note> alone was left. No queſtion there was then, and hath bene ſince, and euer will be a Church of God, ſo long as Chriſt ſhall raigne at the right hand of the father, and yet it was not then ſeene in outward viſible pompe, but rather ſeemed as deſolate, (as the Prophet Helias himſelfe ſuppoſed,) and as no Churche indeede: but it was ſaide to Helias that there were reſerued ſeuen thouſand men that had not bowed their knees to Baall. So that there was euen then a church, which yet was not ſeene with outward ſhining pompe, and when the Prophet himſelfe began therewith alſo to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed.</p>
            <p>Where was the Church in the time of Chriſt and hys Apoſtles, when the ſhepheard was taken, and the ſheepe was ſcattered and diſperſed? When the gliſtring outward ſhewe was in the high Prieſtes, Scribes, and Phariſees? And yet the Church obſcured, was the true Churche, and not the ſynagoue of the Scribes, Phariſees, &amp; high prieſts that excelled in outward gorgeous ſhew.</p>
            <p>Thus there is no queſtion but that the true Church may be, and yet not appeare in outward pompe of ſhew and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to the eye. For where was our church in Quene Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries dayes, as in all other times of perſecutions in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the worlde beſides: Is there not a Church though it be not ſeene, nor ſhewed in outward and eminent bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but lyeth as it were hid, darkened, &amp; ſcattered abroad?
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1028:7"/> The Church was then perſecuted, and many then like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Martirs of the true Church indeede induced the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of that romiſh religion, ſo that ſome were banniſhed, and other fled into other nations for ſuccour, and ſome indured martyrdome at home, ſome other hid themſelues, but the whole Church generallie was vexed and oppreſſed. And therefore when our Church was perſecuted it is a good ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument I thinke to ſay there was a Church ouerwhelmed with tyrannicall malice. Is anie man ſo buzzard like, or ſo blockiſhly blind, that will ſay there is no ſinne at al, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſometime couered with a cloud? or that there is no fire at all becauſe it is ſometime raked vp in imbers? our Church may be, and yet not ſeene, not knowne to be, by reaſon of darkeneſſe, and palpable blindneſſe, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that ouer ſhadowed the light thereof: ſo that by reaſon of clowdie darkeneſſe that grewe, the Church could not ſhine to the viewe of others, though in it ſelfe it were inligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened from God with a ſecret hidden and vnapparent light many ages togither.</p>
            <p>Thus by expreſſe teſtimonie of ſcripture thou ſeeſt that a Church may be, yea a true Church may be, though it be not eminent in apparent ſhew: for God doth ſhew the bright beames thereof in time, and cauſeth it to ſhine in perfect bewtie: for, it is neither deuill nor pope, nor prelate, nor po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate, no power, nor pollicie that is able vtterly to roote it out from the earth, for the God of heauen is the ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender and moſte puiſſant preſeruer thereof againſt all the diueliſh braynes, that doe nothing els but deuiſe the vtter ruine and deſtruction thereof, if they could tell which way. To theſe men therefore me thinkes Gameliel, a doctor of the lawe, ſhould ſatiſfie anſwering in the like caſe to the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, who tooke counſell to put Peter and the reſt of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles to death, for their preaching in the name of Ieſus. Let them alone ſaith he, for if this<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 5, 28</note> worke be of men, it will ſurely come to naught, if of God, you cannot diſſolue it leaſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1028:8"/> you be found to fight againſt God. As long therefore as our religion is builded, not vpon men, but vpon God, in vayne doe papiſtes looke for the ouerthrow of that whereof God himſelfe purpoſeth to vphold.</p>
            <p>They obiect as contrarie vnto vs the antient fathers by whoſe conſenting voyce, if the debate were to be ended, the better part of the victorie to ſpeake moſte modeſtly, would bend to our ſide: but whereas manie thinges haue bin well and wiſely written of thoſe fathers, and ſomething hath happened to them which is woont to happen to men, theſe kinde natured children according to the rightneſſe they haue both of wit and iudgement, doe worſhip onely their faultes and errours, and thoſe thinges which are well ſpoken, they eyther vtterly reiect, or els miſchieuouſle corrupt with their baſtard glozes and interpretations. And no maruell though they thus deale with the fathers who were but men, when they dare be bolde to adde to, to take from, to curtoll &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt in like ſort the ſacred ſcriptures of God himſelfe, as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward ſhalbe declared. But the papiſtes are ſo drowned in their owne ſenſuall blindneſſe, they are ſo addicted onely to the outward eye that they can ſee no true token of the true church: they ſhew themſelues to be men in that rather then they will haue no Church they will build it vpon men when they want the word of God for their foundation: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon in trueth the true Church is builded: but of the ſame fountain of ignorance is it that they call our religion newe becauſe it appeared not in outward ſhewe along time toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as their painted Church hath done, to whome we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that it is, new to them to whome the Goſpel is new: And wheras it hath long lien hid vnknown, and as it were buried, that was the fault of the vngodlineſſe of the world, but nowe ſith it is by the bountifulneſſe of God reſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, it ought by right of full reſtitution to receiue againe the due title of antiquitie: And herein the papiſtes do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt iniurie vnto vs: who conuey our religion (farre before
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1028:8"/> theirs) namely from the mouth of God, and the prophets, of Chriſt, and his apoſtles by a lawfull conueyance written with the finger of God, ſealed with the blood of his ſonne, and deliuered vnto vs by the handes of the prophetes, and apoſtles, ſo that we haue the writinges of God, lawfully ſealed and deliuered, to giue in euidence for the trueth of that faith that we profeſſe, the truth whereof is confirmed by the myracles that are extant in ſcriptures, wrought by Chriſt and his apoſtles, for the eſtabliſhing of his doctrine foreuer. So that I truſt the Papiſtes will not driue vs to other myracles: for all the myracles that euer were done before, either in the time of Moſes and the Prophetes, or Chriſt and his apoſtles, for confirming of the doctrine that they ſhould teach, vpon which doctrine already confirmed by innumerable myracles, ſignes, and wonders, Wee reſt and ſtay our ſelues as vpon a moſt ſure anchor and infallible foundation, which can neuer faile nor fall.</p>
            <p>They haue charged our doctrine, as the welſpring of troubles, vprores, and contentions, and tearmed it moſt ſlaunderouſly, a Doctrine of Libertines, and licentious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie. But who knoweth not that theſe are euident and apparant badges of their Romiſh religion? Dooth not daylie experience teach vs that the Romaine Ieſuits, and Seminaries of Rome, doo diſquiet not onely England, but all Europe, with erecting vprores, and monſtrous treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and treaſons in peaceable common-weales, with ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to ſhead innocent blood, to pull crownes from lawfull annointed Princes, and ſetting ſubiectes (if they could) in rebellious troupes to bid battaile againſt their lawful So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignes?</p>
            <p>But it is an hard matter to take Hercules club out of his hand: and to wreath from Princes their crownes is more impoſſible: but in raiſing warre againſt God, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointer of Princes, and preſeruer of their regal Scepters, is far leſſe hope to get a victorie.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:1028:9"/>
            <p>Therefore to the turbulent ſpirited Papiſtes Elias hath taught vs to anſwere, that it is not we that haue<note n="c" place="margin">1. King 18</note> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Iſraell, but themſelues that wraſtle againſt the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God. And whereas they vrge vpon vs a doctrine of liberties, and licentiouſneſſe, they throwe that vppon vs which is appropriated and peculier vnto themſelues one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: For our religion teacheth a true faith towards God, and good and godly conuerſation among men: but all the Romiſhe Catholikes if they bee once reconciled to the Sea of Rome, there is no trueth in their mouthes, nor faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in their heartes, they may ſweare and forſweare: for <hi>Fides non eſt ſeruanda cum haereticis,</hi> as they with as much rage, as litle reaſon tearme vs: yea, what villanie may they not commit? They may ſinne all monſtrous ſinnes of the world, and iuſtifie it when they haue done: ſo that they may ſinne, and that with authoritie. They may haue a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don from the pope, and a diſpenſation alſo for money, to commit all filthineſſe and kindes of naughtineſſe, adulterie, robberie, murther, treaſons, rebellions: And what villanie is there that they may not commit with boldneſſe, by vertue of their vitious and moſt peſtilent religion. For a popes par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don will ſalue all.</p>
            <p>Doo wee not ſee it euident that the pope ſendeth his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates hither to perſwade the people to a wrong faith, to whiſper in their eares treachery and treaſon againſt a moſt naturall prince and Soueraigne. And to ſuch fellowes as like hereof, they graunt pardons, and take it a matter meritorious in heauen: But who is ſo blind that dooth not ſee the peruerſnes, and ſenſuall beaſtineſſe of their Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh religion: who, when they are able no longer to ſtand vpright, and to maintaine the pompe of the Pope, but that his kingdom beginneth to fall, being already ſhaken, when by the power of the word of God, the glory of their church beginneth to decay and fade away: then they are driuen to deuiſe newe ſubtilties, and becauſe their doctrine cannot
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1028:9"/> pleaſe God, they endeuour another while to ſee if they can pleaſe men withall,</p>
            <p>Wherein (good reader) I beſeech thee conſider with me, vpon what good foundation the Church of Rome is buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and how well the pope (that vainely boſteth himſelfe to be Peters ſucceſſour, diſchargeth the office of a true apoſtle. The papiſtes and Romaniſtes they contend with ſtretched out voice, and fight with all the violence they can, to erect and vphold the vaniſhing, and all tottering glorie of the pope. This they cannot doo (they thinke) vnleſſe they haue the peoples heartes: and they perſwade themſelues, that the people of the other ſide will neuer be reconciled to their Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church, vnleſſe their religion be eaſie, plauſible, and pleaſant to the outward ſight, and delight of the fleſh.</p>
            <p>Hereupon haue they graunted their Bulles, their diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, and all other their licentious doctrines, which geue free leaue and authoritie to commit any ſinne or ſinnes, for as long or as ſhort a time as they liſted, ſo that they might take their choiſe of pleaſant ſinnes, to ſport themſelues at their pleaſure and conuenient leiſure: which to atchieue, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they muſt pay good currant coyne for.</p>
            <p>Behold gentle Reader, the two pillers of the church of Rome: <hi>viz.</hi> The glorie and riches of their proude Pope, and prelates was one: and the libertie preached to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, was the other. So that the pope (I thinke) went about to builde a kingdome for himſelfe on earth, rather then to build a church for God in heauen.</p>
            <p>Hereupon is he magnified with ſo many titles: Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, after he began to growe in ambition, he vſurped the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Supremacie ouer all kinges, princes, and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of the world. And when the pope had all this iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and preheminence, what was it els but to ſay with the Whore of Babylon<note n="d" place="margin">Reue. 18.8</note> Sit as Queene. I wonder that all the Papiſtes of the world are not aſhamed of their vnholye father, whoſe kingdome, whoſe Church, whoſe religion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1028:10"/> is onely to preach libertie and licentious kinde of liuing to the people, ſeeking his owne onlie glorie and renowne, and not the glorie of God.</p>
            <p>This is that the Ieſuits fight for, that the Seminaries perſwade and contend for, that the papiſtes boaſt of, that they dare challenge al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world in diſputation for the defence thereof, namely the erecting of the downfalling pride of the Pope, in their ſubtill perſwaſions to reconcile ſillie &amp; vnſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoules vnto their Romiſh Sea. They can paint out the honour of Rome with moſt princelie building, in the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of their Pope, with more then kinglie tytles, and the glory of their ſplendant Church with no leſſe eloquence: inſomuch as they haue made their tongues as ſweete as muſicke to enchant, and their reaſon nothing but ſophiſtry to deceiue: of whom I wiſh all men to take heede, as of ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening wolues, and to flie them as venemous ſerpents. For the true Church of God dooth not ſtande in ſuch outward glyſtering pompe, as theſe men would make beleeue, but in trueth of the word of God deliuered in ſacred ſcriptures, as heretofore hath bene declared. But all the pomp where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Romaine Ieſuits, Seminaries and papiſtes doo ſo aduance their proude Pope withall, and calling their Church the mother Church, What dooth it els repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto vs, but the glorious ſtate of the Whore of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, which was clothed with<note n="e" place="margin">Reue. 17.4</note> purple, and decked with golde, with pretious ſtones, and pearles, hauing a cuppe of golde in her hand full of th'abhominations and vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of filthineſſe, and in her forhead was written, not the mother Church, but great Babylon, the mother of forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and of abhominations of the earth?</p>
            <p>O, but I doo the Pope great iniury: for, he calleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <hi>Seruus ſeruorum,</hi> the ſeruant of ſeruants: but what matter is it to cal himſelf ſo in name, when in deed he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf <hi>Rex regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> a king of kings, and a Lord aboue all nations, as his title of ſupremacie, his vſurped authoritie of-excommunication
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1028:10"/> of princes, his putting downe of kinges, and giuing their kingdoms away to whome he liſt doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly bewray. So that this is but a miſt caſt ouer mens eies, to blind fold men from beholding the vſurped princeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Pope.</p>
            <p>In trueth the Church of Rome ſauoureth of too much earthly pompe to haue any part in the true church of God, though it boaſt neuer ſo much and truſt in lying words, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the temple of the Lord, the temple of the Lord, the temple of the Lord, The papiſtes can ſay that concerning Rome they haue the teſtimonie of Paule, who in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Romanes writeth to al that be in Rome &amp; calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 1.7.</note> beloued of God, called ſaints: but what profiteth it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that in times paſt there was a true ſpouſe of Chriſt in Rome, ſith now and manie yeares ſince it is become an adultreſſe and hath forſaken her firſt loue &amp; her firſt faith? But al this is outcountenanced with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authority of the pope being Peters ſucceſſor as he glorieth. And the pope he cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth the Apoſtolike Sea, ſo that hee will be Peters ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour: and yet <hi>vicarius dei:</hi> what is this els but to aſſure vs that Antichriſt ſhall ſit in the Temple<note n="g" place="margin">Theſſ 24.</note> of God, as God, boaſting himſelfe to be God. The Phariſees in Chriſtes dayes could ſay who can forgiue ſinnes but God: and yet the Pope, hee will arrogate vnto himſelfe that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to wreath from kinges their crownes and ſcepters: what is this but to ſit in the temple of God as God, and boaſting himſelf to be God. Now how well he diſchargeth the office of an Apoſtle, I think al men vnderſtand he brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to be Peters ſucceſſour: but what glory is it to be Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſucceſſour in place and not to retaine the doctrine and performe the office of the Apoſtle Peter. It is the maner of papiſtes altogether to glorie of names, perſons and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſuch outward titles, &amp; they neuer looke to the trueth of inward puritie, ſo that al there religion is nothing els, but a painted ſchulchre, fayre to the eye, but within full of rotten
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1028:11"/> bones: becauſe the pope was ſucceſſour to a good Apoſtle: It followeth not no more then an vſurper of a kingdome ſhalbe ſaid a lawful king, becauſe he is a ſucceſſour to a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full king: Though Peter were a true apoſtle, yet the pope may be a falſe Apoſtle, and that the Pope is a falſe Apoſtle appeareth by the notes of a true and falſe Apoſtle: Peter had his calling from Chriſt to be an Apoſtle, and ſo entred Peter into the Apoſtleſhip: For Chriſt is the<note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 10.1</note> dore, &amp; who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer entereth not in by the doore, but climeth vp ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, the ſame is a theefe and a robber: therefore let the Pope ſhew that he entred in by the dore, or els hee is not like Peter, a lawful Apoſtle: In doctrine, how the Pope and Peter agree is ſoone ſeene.</p>
            <p>Peter ſaith if<note n="i" place="margin">1. Pet. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> anie man ſpeake, let him ſpeake as the words of God: the pope hee blotteerth out his owne traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his vnwritten verities, and vomiteth out the puddle of his owne brayne: yea he, wil preache matter contrarie to the word of God, and peruert the worde of God: as when Paule ſayth, and the whole Scripture agreeing with hym, that by the<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 3.20</note> workes of the lawe no fleſh ſhalbe iuſtified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, the Pope and Papiſtes holde and teache, that good woorkes are meritorious: yea, and that there bee woorkes of ſuperogation able to ſaue both themſelues and others alſo they may ſo abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with ſuch ſuperfluitie of good workes. Yea worſe then all this, they holde and teache, and teach other to practiſe (which is moſt horrible blaſphemie) that bad workes are alſo meritorious, namely that treaſon in ſubiects, and murthering of their lawfull Chriſtian So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, is not onely lawful but alowable: yea, commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: nay, more than ſo, meritorious in heauen, which doctrine as it is moſte blaſphemous, ſo the practiſe thereof is moſte damnable and dangerous, abhorring from nature, which teacheth euerie ſubiect to feare and honour his prince, as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bindeth the ſonne to feare and honour his father, for <hi>princeps eſt patriae parens:</hi> degenerating from the law of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1028:11"/> all nations for it is lawfull and meritorious for a papiſticall Romaniſt treacherouſly to murder his holy father the pope: yea rather more, if of euils the leaſt be to be choſen, then it is for a ſworne ſubiect to be falſe and traiterous to ſo chriſtian a prince, Meere repugnant to all Scripture, yea contrary to the doctrine of Peter himſelfe, whoſe doctrine the pope muſt obey and teach, if in ſucceſſion hee will be accompted a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Apoſtle of Chriſt. harken O ye Papiſts, and liſten what Peter teacheth you, follow his doctrine &amp; let not the popes bare name of holy father deceiue you any more, nor the name of the Apoſtolicke Sea, for they are but lying wordes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue you: Compare the Apoſtleſhip of Peter with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtleſhip of the Pope, and then if you find him contrarie, though he be Peters ſucceſſour, reiect him and tread hys doctrine vnder feete.</p>
            <p>The wordes of Peter are thus: be<note n="m" place="margin">1. Pet. 2 13.</note> ſubiect therefore, (ſaith he) to euery humain creature whether it be to the king as to the chiefe: or to relers, as to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be ſet in authoritie, for the puniſhment of them that doe ill, and the praiſe of them that doe good: againe in the ſame chapter he ſaith, honour all men, loue brotherly charitie, feare God, honour the king: againe, he commandeth ſeruantes to ſubmit themſelues in all feare vnto their maſters, not onely (ſaith he) if they be good, but alſo though they be froward.</p>
            <p>If a froward maiſter be to be honoured and feared of his ſeruaunt, much more ought the perſon of a kinde and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Soueraigne be had in moſt reuerent eſtimation of all ſubiectes: conſidering that the perſon of a Prince on earth is the image of God in heauen: that ſhe is a perſon of migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie maieſtie, of puiſſant magnificence, and of moſt gliſtring princely royaltie, who being placed in her throne by God, by whome <hi>Reges regnant, &amp; principes dominantur,</hi> is impoſſible to be thruſt out by the power or pollicie of men, no not of the deuill himſelfe, nor all his adherentes: for that muſt needes ſtand, which God hath ſtabliſhed, but that may
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1028:12"/> eaſily fall which men onely haue erected: heauen and earth may paſſe, but not one iote of the word of God ſhall periſhe but ſhalbe fulfilled: They therefore may aſwell thinke it as poſſible to pul God out of heauen, as it is to remoue a lawful annoynted prince from beſide the ſeat, wherein God himſelf ſtablified her: The vaine hope of the papiſts therefore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed, and the falſe Apoſtleſhip of the pope confuted by the faithfull Apoſtle Peter, let vs proceede further to compare them together.<note n="n" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.11</note> Beloued ſaith Peter, I exhort you as ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and pilgrimes abſtaine from fleſhly luſtes which fight againſt the ſoule: And againe he ſaith,<note n="o" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.15</note> As he which called you is holy, ſo be ye alſo ſanctified in all conuerſation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſayth he, it is written<note n="p" place="margin">Leuit. 11 4 4</note> be ye holy as I am holy: So that Peter admitteth no vncleanneſſe, nor diſpenſeth with anie ſinne, but reproueth all and onely alloweth ſanctimonie of life and conuerſation, and hee bringeth in <hi>ſcriptum eſt</hi> alſo for the warrant of his doctrine, I would all that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend themſelues to be his ſucceſſours would doe the like: and giue the like wholeſome ſound admonitions and preceptes then ſhould not men eyther for loue, or money haue pardons, diſpenſations, commiſſions, with authoritie to commit moſt diueliſh murder: accompting that for meritorious, which is moſt monſtrous, and meriteth in trueth a moſte bloudie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge for the body, and eternall tormentes for the ſoule, if it ſhould be but ſo much as conceaued in the imagination: What the office of a true Apoſtle is, Peter deſcribeth in his fift Chapter.<note n="q" place="margin">1. Pet. 5.1.</note> The elders that be amongeſt you, I which am alſo an elder exhorte, feede, as muche as in yours, the flocke of Chriſt, not compelledly but willingly, not couetous of filthy gaine, but of a readie minde, not as exerciſing lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ouer the clergie, but that yee may be<note n="r" place="margin">2. Cor, 4, 24</note> examples of the flocke: If Peter ſhewing himſelfe that he is an elder, doe clayme no Lordſhip in hys Apoſtleſhip, how commeth it to paſſe then that the pope his pretended ſucceſſour, claymeth not onely a lordſhip and dominion in Rome, but a litle of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1028:12"/> ouer all nations. The Papiſtes anſwereth at chriſt ſaid vnto Peter, Thou<note n="s." place="margin">Mat, i6, 18</note> art Peter, and vpon this Rocke I will build my Church, and the gates of hel ſhal not preuaile againſt it: and I wil geue to thee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> keies of the kingdom of heauen. And whatſoeuer thou bindeſt on earth, ſhal be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in heauen, and whatſoeuer thou looſeſt on earth, ſhall be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But can theſe words of binding &amp; looſing giue a ſupremacie and kingdome vnto the Pope, and not to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whoſe ſucceſſour he is? For we heard before from Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters own mouth, that he claymeth nor alloweth, but diſclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth and diſſwadeth ſuch exerciſed lordſhip ouer the Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie. So that neither did, he affect ſuch proud titles of honour Lordſhip, and ſuperioritie, but ſought rather, as he wiſhed all other, to be examples of mildneſſe and good conuerſation.</p>
            <p>How can wee thinke that Chriſt ſhould giue ſuch Lord-like authoritie, when Chriſt telleth his diſciples contending among themſelues who ſhould ſeeme to bee the geeateſt: The<note n="t" place="margin">Luke, 22, 25 Mat, 20.25 Marke, 15.24</note> Kinges of nations (ſaith he) beare Lordſhip, but it ſhall not be ſo with you: but he that will be the greateſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, let him be as the leaſt, or as a ſeruant.</p>
            <p>Now if neither Peter had the ſuperiority but forbiddeth it, as teaching al humilitie, being taught by Chriſt his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings of nations are to beare the lordſhip: &amp; his apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſhould be ſo far from contending for primacy on earth, that they ſhould rather be as ſeruants appointed to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to the Church of Chriſt, to build a kingdom for God in heauen: If neither Peter had it, and if Chriſt alſo forbad it: ſhewing, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdomes belong to the kinges of the nations: how can any man gather, that Chriſts meaning was to giue that to Peter, which he forbiddeth Peter &amp; al the reſt of the apoſtles? If Peter neuer had this authority, I maruel much how the papiſts can poſſibly conueigh that to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope which his predeceſſour neuer had: for they affirm the popes autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to be aboue al kings of the earth, ſupreame head of the Church, and vniuerſall biſhop of the whole world; but how
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1028:13"/> far theſe vſurped tytles were from the affection of the true apoſtle Peter, the humilitie of Peter, the deuine exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Peter. And the former commandement of Chriſt to al the Apoſtles dooth ſufficiently declare: for neither coulde Chriſt giue that authoritie of Primacie which himſelfe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad, nor Peter take that which was not giuen him, and which he neither vſed, nor ſo much as deſired in affection: neither conſequently can the Pope, his pretended ſucceſſour deriue that vnto him, which neuer belonged to his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor.</p>
            <p>It cannot therefore be, that the power of binding and loo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing, ſhould ſignifie the ſupremacie of earthly kingdomes, to ſet vp and pull downe whom he liſt: for (as hath bene alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy prooued) Peter is ſo far from that arrogance, that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe giueth a double charge to the contrarie: namely to feare God, and to honour the king, as one that is woorthy to haue the chiefeſt roome: for Chriſt had taught Peter, and Peter no doubt learned it, that Lordſhip and dominion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed vnto the kinges of Nations.</p>
            <p>The power therefore of binding and looſing is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Peter alone, but to all the Apoſtles, and ſeemeth to be expounded in the xx. of Iohn, where Chriſt, after hee had breathed vpon his apoſtles, and ſaid, Receiue<note n="v" place="margin">Iohn. 20.22</note> ye the holie Ghoſt, he had ſaid before, As my Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you. He addeth furthermore, that Whoſe ſinnes yee remit, they are remitted: and whoſe ſinnes yee retaine, they are retained. And this power of binding and looſing, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting and retaining, was not appropriate vnto their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or vnto their places, but vnto the office of their Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip, and vnto their preaching of the Goſpell. For Saint Paule ſaith that the<note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 1 16 1. Cor. 1.21.</note> Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt is the power of God vnto ſaluation to euery on that beleeueth.</p>
            <p>The Gaoler demanded of Paule and Silas, what he ſhould doo, that hee might be ſaued, they anſwered,<note n="y" place="margin">Act. 16.31,</note> Beleeue in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaued and thy
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1028:13"/> houſhold. When Peter had preached vnto the people, they began to be pricked in their hearts, they demanded of him, and of the other Apoſtles: Men and brethren, what ſhall we doo? Peter anſwered,<note n="a" place="margin">Act 2 38</note> Repent, and be baptiſed euery man in the name of Ieſus Chriſt for the remiſſion of ſins, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ye the gift of holy Ghoſt. Be it known vnto you <hi>b</hi> men and brethren (ſaith Paule) that thorow this man (ſpeaking of Chriſt) is preached vnto you the remiſſion of ſinnes, and that euery one that beleeueth, ſhall thorow him be iuſtified from all thinges, from which he could not be iuſtified by the lawe of Moſes.</p>
            <p>So that we ſee, that remiſſion of ſins is by the preaching of the Goſpell to the faithfull: and that <hi>contra,</hi> Their <hi>c</hi> ſinnes are retained and bound with chaines thereof, that are Infidels, obſtinate, and vnrepentant, that haue no faith to take hold of ſaluation preached by the Apoſtles and paſtors of the Church.</p>
            <p>But (ſay they) When Chriſt gaue vnto Peter by ſpeciall name, the keies of binding and looſing, hee thereby made Peter the Prince of the whole church. The anſwere is eaſie ſie, for it is proued before, that Chriſt gaue the power of bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; looſing to al the Apoſtles, and why at this time Chriſt ſaid vnto Peter that he would giue to him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> keies by ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al name, the reaſon was, as appeareth by the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance of the text, becauſe when Chriſte demaunded of his Apoſtles, Whom ſay ye that I am, Simon Peter anſwered, thou art Chriſt the ſonne of the liuing God: For Peter anſwered in the name of all the apoſtles, and Chriſt likewiſe gaue him the keies in the name of all. And ſo Cyprian and Auguſtine, two of the Fathers expound it, that Chriſt did it not for this purpoſe, to preferre one man before an other, but ſo to ſet foorth the vnitie of the Church: for ſo ſaith Cyprian, that God in the perſon of one, gaue the keyes to all, to ſignifie the vnitie of the Church. Auguſtine ſaith, When the Apoſtles were all aſked, onely Peter anſwered, Thou art Chriſt: and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1028:14"/> it is ſaid to him, I will giue thee the keies, as though hee alone had receiued the power of binding and looſing, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he being one ſtandeth one, for all, And he receiued the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all, as bearing the perſon of vnitie: therefore one for all, becauſe there is vnitie in all.</p>
            <p>I truſt theſe Fathers will ſatiſfie the Papiſtes, if they be not obſtinately malitious, and froward children that in the power of the keies of Peter gayned no ſuperioritie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the reſt of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Act, 15, 5 1, pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 5, 1 Act, 11, 3 Actes, 8, 24 Gal, 1 &amp; 2, cap,</note>Run ouer all that remaineth written, and you ſhall finde nothing els but that hee was one of the twelue, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall with the reſt, and their fellowe, but not their Lorde. I woonder therefore that the Pope and Papiſtes will force that vpon Peter, which Peter neuer had, nor meant to take vppon himſelfe, which Chriſt neuer meant to giue him, nor to any other, viz. to be the Prince and head of the Church: for he hath left this tytle to no other but himſelfe.</p>
            <p>This that Chriſt ſaith, Thou art Peter, and vpon this rocke I wil build my Church, imprehendeth no other thing of Peter, but that which Paule, and Peter himſelfe ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to al Chriſtians: for Paule maketh Chriſt the chiefe &amp;<note n="d" place="margin">Epheſ, c, 20</note> corner ſtone, vpon which they are builded together, that grow into an holy temple to the Lord. And Peter biddeth vs to be liuely<note n="e" place="margin">1, Pet, 2.3</note> ſtones, builded vpon that liuely, choſen and precious ſtone, Chriſt Ieſus. So when Peter had anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the demand, that hee was Chriſt the ſonne of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God: then ſaid Chriſt, Bleſſed art thou<note n="f" place="margin">Mat, 16, 7</note> Simon Bar-Iona, for fleſh and blood hath reualed this to thee, but my father which is in heauen. And I ſay vnto thee that thou art Peter, and vpon this rocke will I build my Church, and the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt it. So that ſtill the Church is builded vpon that confeſſion and anſwer that Peter made: viz. Vpon Chriſt the ſon of the liuing God: alſo the <hi>g</hi> rocke is ſaid to be Chriſt by eſpeciall wordes in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the Corinthians.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:1028:14"/>
            <p>And Chriſt himſelfe ſayth by ſpeciall wordes alſo, that he that heareth hys wordes and doth them, hath like a wiſe man builded his houſe vppon a rocke, ſo that Chriſt and hys word be<note place="margin">Mat, 7, 24, 25</note> the rock wherevpon the Churche of Chriſt is builded: For the Church is not builded <hi>ſuper Petrum,</hi> but <hi>ſuper petram:</hi> that is Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of the liuing God, whome Peter confeſſed.</p>
            <p>If Peter then be not the head of the Church, downe muſt fall the title of the vniuerſall Biſhop of all the Church, which title the pope proudly hath vſurped, as deriued from Peter, who was content to be a member of the Churche, and not the head thereof, but the ſwelling ambition of the Pope is ſo monſtrous, that hee neither careth to commit treaſon againſt chriſtian princes, but moſt proudly hee will intrude himſelfe into the ſeate and throne of God himſelfe, and he will be head of the Churche to dye for it: but I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in the end he will ſcarſe be ſo much as the foot, or one of the toes of the Churche, his blaſphemie is ſo monſtrous and ſo intollerable.</p>
            <p>If then (ſillie Pope) thou wilt be head of the whole Churche, ſhewe which way thou makeſt title, for Peter from whome thou claymeſt was content to be a member of the Church: And thou becauſe thou canſt not be a member of the church, moſt proudly claymeſt to be the head: &amp; becauſe thou canſt not be the head, thou wilt be no part of the church at all. I beleeue the conſequent: dareſt thou proud pope with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all authoritie derogate ſo much from the glory and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of Chriſt, as to take from Chriſt his crown, &amp; to ſet it vpon thy head moſt traiterouſly, and thinkeſt thou that he will not trample thee vnder his feete? doth not Paule to the Epheſians ſpeake in plaine t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>armes that God raiſed Chriſt from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead, and ſet him at his right hand in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly places aboue all principalities, &amp; powers, and lordſhips, and euery name that is named not onely in this world, but in the world to come, and hath ſubmitted all thinges vnder his feete, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1028:15"/> hath made him head aboue all thinges to the Churche, which is his body, the fulneſſe of him that filleth all in all. If Chriſt be the head of the Church, as this text doth moſt plainly proue, then ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not the pope be the head of the church in earth, as hee proudly vſurpeth: for there can be but one head of the Church, and that head is Chriſt: ſo that it is the ſole appropriated title of Chriſt to be the head of his church on earth, and euerie where, for God hath giuen this title to neither man nor angell, nor archangell, but to Chriſt one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whom he rayſed from the dead. Looke through the whole life of Peter, looke through all his Epiſtles and doctrine, and thou ſhalt finde in him all the markes of a true and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Apoſtle: his minde humble, not eleuated with pride: his doctrine ſound, which he had receiued from Chriſt: his counſell good: his admonitions wholeſome: his Epiſtles moſt deuine.</p>
            <p>The pope his boaſting ſucceſſor cannot abide the charge of preaching ſincerely the word of God: but yet will hee be an Apoſtle, as touching the place, and retaine the name of an Apoſtle, and when a man is no more an Apoſtle, and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uera</hi> wanteth both the doctrine and ſincere minde of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, what is this elſe but to be a falſe Apoſtle, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truder into the Church of God? What his doctrine is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, to recite al were to tedious, and almoſt infinit: their idolatrous maſſe, their inuented purgatorie deuiſed onely to purge mens purſſes, not their ſoules, their bowing to idols, their interceſſion of ſaintes, their freewill, their iuſtification by workes, nay their workes of ſuperogation and infinite more: what doe all theſe but make voyd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe of Chriſt, and diſanull the grace of God, repugnant plainely againſt the law of Moſes and the ſacred ſcriptures? But who may ſpeake againſt him in anie thing? who may tell him that God commandeth we ſhould not<note n="k" place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> bow down nor worſhip carued Images, and if he leaue out this ſecond commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cleane out of the booke becauſe it maketh agaynſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1028:15"/> him, who can reproue him? In his abſurd doctrne of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantion after the wordes of conſecration vttered who can perſwade him but that the bread is the verie body of Chriſt? and the wine is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verie bloud, though Chriſt call it plainly the <hi>l</hi> fruite of the vine in plaine tearmes? Who may tell him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhould onely teach the godly doctrine of Chriſt as a faithful Apoſtle, and not his vnwritten verities nor cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll the ſcriptures of God, nor yet diſpence with any thing therein contained? who may tell him of his charters of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, his diſpenſations to commit cruell and vnnaturall murders againſt Chriſtian Princes, rebellions, robberies, adulteries and all the villanies of the world, and all this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pretenſed colour of the ſupremacie (which Peter neuer had) ouer the Church of God ouer all Princes and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, yea and I thinke aboue God, himſelfe? for what is this els, but to chop and chaunge, and to vſe at his pleaſure the ſacred word of God, and to abuſe it to all vngodlineſſe and wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Their anſwere is ſhort, that the Scriptures are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by generall counſels, and they and the pope make the Church, and the Church cannot erre. And whatſoeuer therefore they ſhall ſay or decree, that is the worde of God, and to be reuerenced as an oracle from heauen whatſoeuer it be: And hereupon is builded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>implicita fides</hi> of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man papiſtes, to beleeue as the Church beleeueth, is fayth good inough for a papiſt: This argument is verie <hi>pitha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorium, Ipſe dixit: ergo verum eſt:</hi> O ſubtill papiſtes, O ſimple and deceiued people, O moſte diueliſhe and peſtilent religion, thus to bewitch mens heartes, and to caſt a miſt before their eyes, to blindfolde them in ſuch pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted doctrine: And the more to colour this their fraud and apparent deceite they haue eſtabliſhed ignorance, for the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of deuotion, and images they haue made lay mens bookes, and as for the Bible, that ſhalbe read to the people in an vnknowne toong, as in Latine: O diueliſh deuiſe of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1028:16"/> Sathan, O helliſh darkenes: Not the deuill himſelfe could haue inuented a more ſubtil &amp; yet a moſt pernitious religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Is ignoraunce the mother of deuotion, when Chriſt calleth it the mother of error, ſaying, to the Saduces, you<note place="margin">Mat. 22 29.</note> erre not knowing the ſcriptures? Can an vnlearned man ſayth Paule, ſay Amen to thy ſeruice vttered in an vnknown toonge, when he knoweth not what thou ſaieſt? and he ſayth plainly that there is no<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> edification in ſuch vnknowne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, howe can theſe men boaſt that they edifie the people then when the people ſay Amen they know not to what, and their <hi>implicita fides</hi> beleeueth they knowe not what: they tell them the church cannot erre, and this is ſufficient for them, if you will goe anie further the Church muſt anſwere. O ſilly Romaniſtes, ſo much ſeduced by that deluding Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, wherevpon is your Church builded? vpon the pope as the head of the church, and the generall counſelles. Peter neuer claymed to be the head of the Church, hee neuer had that authority giuen him, nay it was denied him to ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it: And Chriſt onely is the head of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church as hath bin proued before, <hi>Ergo</hi> the pope hath no ſuch preheminence. As touching their generall counſels wherewith they binde mens conſciences, as with cordes, how can they proue thoſe counſels to be autentically true? for whatſoeuer it be, that is decreed by them, they make them as oracles and neceſſarie concluſions of the trueth, though they diſagree neuer ſo muche from the Scriptures: for ſuche matters muſt not be called into queſtion, for they hold it as a principle, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> from the determination of a counſell there can be no appellation: but what if they erre? They ſay they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not erre: whie? Becauſe they be the Church: who alloweth it? Will they prooue themſelues to bee the Church, who in their blinde and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueliſhe doctrine and conuerſation, ſhewe themſelues to be the Synagogue of Sathan? I knowe not, and I am ſure themſelues will neuer be able to prooue: For the word of God is that which muſt trie out the trueth of the religion,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1028:16"/> and Church of God. For as for building faith vpon general Councels, it is a verie feeble foundation, and (no queſtion) they might erre, and did erre: yea, they are ſomtimes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie one to an other: as the Synod of Conſtantinople ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together vnder Leo the Emperour, iudged, that ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſet vp in Churches ſhould bee ouerthrowen and broken in peeces. A litle afterward the Councel of Nyce which the Empreſſe aſſembled in ſpite of him, decreed that they ſhould be reſtored: both theſe Councels could not c true: and whether of theſe ſhould a man take to be true, or how can he tell which is true, but by that Scripture which is geuen by diuine inſpiration, which is the rule of the Church, and the ſquare of trueth, whereupon the church muſt be builded? els we ſhall neuer knowe what, or which is the trueth.</p>
            <p>Auguſtine ſaith, that the latter Councell can not ſtande without preſent perrill of idolatrie. Epiphanius ſaith, it is a wickedneſſe and abhomination to haue Images ſeene in the Church of Chriſtians. The Councell of Conſtance for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad the Sacrament of the Lordes Supper to be geuen to the lay people, but willed that the Prieſt onely ſhould drinke thereof, which I thinke the Romaniſtes themſelues will not agree vnto.</p>
            <p>Thus becauſe Councels may eaſily erre, ther is no faith to be built vpon them: but all faith, all religion, and the true Church is onely to be built vpon the<note n="o" place="margin">Ephe. 2.20</note> Prophetes and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Chriſt Ieſus being the head corner ſtone, the rocke that neuer falleth nor fadeth: For this is a marke incident to the Church, My<note n="p" place="margin">Iohn, 10.3</note> ſheepe (ſaith Chriſt) will heare my voyce Againe, Chriſt ſaith, He that is of<note n="q" place="margin">Iohn 3.47</note> God heareth Gods wordes, you therefore heare them not (ſaith he) becauſe you are not of God. The ſheepe will followe their good ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, for they knowe his<note n="r" place="margin">iohn. 10.3</note> voice: A ſtranger they will not follow. Therfore the church and true ſpouſe of Chriſt muſt be ſubiect to her head and huſband, enclining to his wil, and gouerned by his word: For the Church which is not buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1028:17"/> vpon the word of Chriſt is built vpon the<note n="s" place="margin">Mat. 7.26.</note> Sand, and ſo ſubiect to a continuall ruine and ouerthrow, as Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe preached in his ſermon: But that which ſtandeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt the rock, the<note n="t" place="margin">Math 16, 18,</note> gates of hell ſhall neuer preuaile a-againſt it, as Chriſt tolde Peter. Trie the ſpirites (ſaith S. Iohn) whether they be of <hi>v</hi> God or no:<note n="f" place="margin">Iohn. 4, 1,</note> for many falſe prophetes are come into the world. Againe, he that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God heareth vs (ſaith S. Iohn) hee that is not of God, heareth not vs: by this we know the ſpirite of trueth, and the ſpirit of errour. The falſe prophetes (ſaith hee) ſpeake of the world, and the world heareth them, becauſe they are of the world: but wee are of God (ſaith he) So that both Iohn and Chriſt ſhew this to be a marke to knowe the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of errour, if they heare not the wordes of Chriſtes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</p>
            <p>Let not the pope therefore deceiue thee (gentle Reader) as though he could not erre: neyther let his generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell ſo bind thy conſcience, without appellation, but that thou be free to trie the ſpirits by the worde of trueth: For many falſe prophetes are come into the world. Trie the gold by the touch ſtone: For be he Pope, be they generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels: yea, be they Angels from heauen, if they preach mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contrarie to the doctrin of Chriſt, beleeue him not: nay, <hi>Anathema eſto,</hi> hold him accurſed, as Paule commandeth thee.</p>
            <p>The Scribes and Phariſes demaunded of Chriſt, why his diſciples tranſgreſſed the traditions of the elders. Chriſt anſwered them, Why doo yee<note place="margin">Math, 15, 2</note> tranſgreſſe the precepts of God thorough your tradition, for God commanded, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Honour father and mother. &amp;c. Hypocrits (ſaith he) wel prophecied Eſayas of you: ſaying, This people commeth neere vnto me with their mouthes, and honoureth me with their lips, but their heartes are farre from me: but in vaine doo they worſhip me, teaching for doctrine, the preceptes of men.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:1028:17"/>
            <p>And is not the religion of Rome as vain a worſhip, when they teach for doctrine, the preceptes of men, viz. of generall Councels, and that we muſt hold them as vndoubted oracles of the holy Ghoſt: and that none muſt mutter againſt them, or gainſay them, vpon paine of a condemned heretik. Yea, they hold, that the word of God is ſubiect to the cenſure of the Church, which (ſay they) is their Pope &amp; generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and whatſoeuer ſenſe they ſet vpon the ſcriptures, is to be receiued for true, without queſtioning againſt it: what is this els but to make the head ſubiect to the foote? the ſheepe to rule their ſhephearde? and the Spouſe which ſhould be ſubiect, to beare authoritie ouer her huſband that ſhoulde be ſoueraigne, her Lord and maiſter to gouerne her after his wil? But herein the Church of Rome ſheweth her ſelf to play the harlot plainly, when ſhe renounceth her head: when ſhe forſaketh her huſband, and runneth a whoring after her owne ymagmations. Iudge then (gentle reader) whether thou think to be the true church, ours that is builded vpon the foundation of Chriſt, the prophetes, and apoſtles, or the church of Rome, that is builded vpon the Pope, his Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, and his generall councels: Ours that acknowledgeth Chriſt to be the onely head thereof, or theirs, who (moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonourably to chriſt) acknowledge the Pope the head ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: Ours that is builded vpon God, ortheirs that is buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon ſlippery men: Ours that admitteth no impuritie, or theirs, who for money, and to ſerue their turne, will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with moſt monſtrous and haynous cruelties: Their religion which ſeeketh and thirſteth after blood, beeing therein like to the Deuill their father, who was a<note n="z" place="margin">Iohn. 8, 44</note> mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer from the beginning, or ours which ſeeketh peace of conſcience in a godly conuerſation: Ours ſeeketh the glory of God: theirs ſeeketh their own pomp, and the glory of the world: Ours giueth free liberty to all to try the truth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of out of the ſacred ſcriptures: they bind mens conſciences with the decrees of their own councels without apellation</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:1028:18"/>
            <p>We ſay with the Prophet Eſay, That all our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is like a defiled cloath: and with Paule, that Chriſt is made vnto vs<note n="a" place="margin">1. Co. 1.3 ct</note> righteouſneſſe by the bountifulnes of God, and wiſedome, and redemption, that as it is written, He that<note n="b" place="margin">Iere 9, 23</note> reioiceth, ſhould reioice in the Lord. We ſay with Chriſt, that no man can come vnto him, vnleſſe it bee<note n="c" place="margin">Iohn. 6, 65</note> giuen him from his father. We ſay alſo with Paule in plaine tearms, that it is<note n="d" place="margin">Phil. z 3</note> God that worketh both the will, and thee deede. They ſay they haue free will of themſelues to good, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God, by I knowe not what blinde light of nature: they haue good woorkes, yea workes of ſuperogation, meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious for themſelues and others alſo: wherein they may boaſt and bragge, but not before<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 4 2</note> God: So we aſcribe all all glorie to God, and they robbe God of his glory and take it to themſelues.</p>
            <p>Peter was commanded to feed the<note n="f" place="margin">ohn 21,</note> flock of Chriſt, and he did according: The Pope he ſtarueth the flocke of Chriſt without any foode, and yet he taketh the fleece: for igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (ſaith he) is the mother of deuotion: and heathen I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols be the bookes that Lay-men muſt looke on, and this is the foode he miniſtreth, and the knowledge and trueth.</p>
            <p>Chriſt biddeth the people, Search the<note n="g" place="margin">Iohn, 5.39</note> Scriptures: the papiſticall church ſaith no: It breedeth ſectes and ſchiſmes, as though they wer wiſer then chriſt. The religion of God is ſincere, holy and pure: for money a man may haue a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and diſpenſation of the Pope for all kindes of beaſtlie vilanies, what dooth this ſhew but that their bellye is theyr God, their kitchin is their roligion? yea, they are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to publiſh murther of chriſtian princes to be a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meritorious: and wherfore contend they for this? but that they may raigne themſelues in earthly pompe, and ſit aboue kings, adorned with large exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded authority. This laſt point is ſuch a blur to their religion, that he is wilfully blind that ſeeth not the falſhood thereof: yea it is ſuch a ſpot to their religion, to giue a commiſſion to commit murder &amp;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1028:18"/> that by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of meritorious: that it bewraieth al the reſt of their religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ful of fraud &amp; deceit &amp; open trecherie. For what man of ſound wit can be perſwaded that he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is a true &amp; faithful apoſtle indeed, can diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in anie ſort with ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen &amp; groſſe faults which are euen odious to the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; readie footpath to bring the bodie into bondage, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule to helliſh torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts? I would wiſh therfore no mans <hi>im plicita fides</hi> to be ſo intangled with his open ſleightes as to beleue him in anie thing, for he ſheweth himſelf <hi>reuera</hi> to be verie Antichriſt in ſuch perſpicuous maner, that no man can doubt thereof, for what doth he els but ſit in the<note n="h" place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.</note> temple of God and boaſt himſelfe to be God, when claiming the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike ſea, he calleth himſelf the vicar of Chriſt in earth? the head of the church? that he cannot erre? that he can forgiue ſinnes? matters that belong peculiarly to God alone: and yet that proud Antichriſt will be extolled with thoſe titles: what is this but to ſit in the ſeate of God as God? Alſo that he claimeth to be <hi>Dux ducum, Rex regum, imperator im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratorum,</hi> that hee hath authoritie to depoſe and ſet vp princes at his pleaſure, to build and ouerthrow kingdomes, what is this but malepertly and moſte blaſphemouſly to thruſt himſelfe into the ſeat of God boaſting himſelfe to be God? for it is God <hi>per quem Reges regnant ac principes dominantur.</hi> But let all the Romaniſtes knowe this, that is alſo written in the ſame Chapter concerning their Antichriſt the pope, that for the decite wherewith hee hath deceaued the inhabitantes of the earth, and for his treaſons and blaſphemies againſt the mighty God, the Lord from heauen ſhall conſume him with the<note n="i" place="margin">2. Theſſ. 28.</note> ſpirite of his mouth, and confound him in the brightneſſe of his comming: Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon muſt<note n="k" place="margin">Reul, 18, 2</note> fall, yea great Babilon muſt fall, and muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an habitation of deuils &amp; a priſon of alvnclean ſpirits. Now let him boaſt that he is Peters ſucceſſor? that maketh him neuer a iote the more lawful apoſtle vnleſſe he perform the office of a ſincere Apoſtle as Peter did:<note n="l" place="margin">Iohn, 10, 1</note> for otherwiſe he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1028:19"/> is a <hi>l</hi> theefe, a robber and a Woolfe that appeareth in ſheepes clothing, of whome Chriſt bad vs beware. And therein he doth nothing els but like the deuils impe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf into an angel of light to deceiue ſimple ſoules. Let them glory in the name of the church, crying that Rome is the mother church, the mother church, what benefite is it to haue the name and to want the thing? for in trueth all their preheminence is onely in names of the church, of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters place in the ſtatelineſſe of their Hierarchie of goodly order, of their carnal cardinals and in ſuch outward pompe and glorie. But (alas) theſe painted clothes bewray the rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedneſſe of their religion: for the churche of God is not builded vpon ſuch outward ſhewes, but vppon ſinceritie of doctrine and conuerſation. Therefore leauing the Lion to be knowne by his clawes, whome times and ſeaſons haue ſo manifeſtly diſcloſed, I counſell thee to forſake the pope and to learne of Peter: build thy faith not vpon the pope who of himſelfe wanteth a foundation, but vpon Paule and Peter and the reſt of the Apoſtles Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the corner ſtone. Take heed of <hi>implicita fides,</hi> &amp; learne thy ſelfe out of the worde of God what thou beleeueſt and wherevpon thy faith is builded: for if it be builded general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vpon men, thy faith is wauering and doubtfull, but if vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, then is it built vpon a rocke, againſt which the gates of hell ſhall neuer preuaile. Followe the aduiſe of Chriſt,<note n="n" place="margin">Iohn, 5, 39</note> Searche the ſcriptures diligently, read them with reuerence in all humilitie, and pray to God earneſtly, ſo ſhall his word be a light vnto thy feete,<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal, i19, 105</note> and a lanterne to thy pathes to direct thee in the way of trueth to keepe thy minde ſincere and thy eye cleere to ſee and diſcerne the trueth from falſhoode, a ſhepheard from a woolfe, a true Apoſtle from a falſe, and Chriſt from Antichriſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1028:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1028:20"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1028:21"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1028:21"/>
            <gap reason="intruder" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page inserted from a different book〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
